Finding Aid for Michigan Public Media (University of Michigan) records, 2008-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Out of the Blue: The Michigan Difference (television program)
2008-2011
Michigan Public Media.
2012091 Bimu
Division within the Office of the Vice President for Communications; comprised of Michigan Radio and the Michigan Channel and also responsible for content contributed to other outlet. Includes three seasons of Out of the Blue: The Michigan Difference, a program that originally aired on the Big Ten Network; also includes archived websites.
112.4 GB
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Michigan Public Media (donor no. 10796 ) in 2011.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Michigan Public Media (MPM) is a division Office of the Vice President for Communications at the University of Michigan. As of 2012, the office was led by Director Stephen Schram and was comprised of Michigan Radio, a National Public Radio news station broadcasting in Ann Arbor, Grand Rapids and Flint; and "The Michigan Channel," the University's cable channel devoted to lifelong learning. Michigan Public Media is also responsible for content contributed to other outlets, including the Big Ten Network (BTN), a joint project between the Big Ten Conference and Fox Entertainment Group. MPM previously produced Michigan Television (WFUM-TV, Flint), but the station was acquired by Central Michigan University in 2009. MPM has won numerous state and national awards for excellence in reporting and innovative programming. Michigan Radio received six awards for excellence in journalism from the Society of Professional Journalists for news coverage in 2005 and eight awards from the Michigan Associated Press for news coverage in 2005.
From 2008-2011, Michigan Public Media contributed three seasons of the program Out of the Blue: The Michigan Difference to the Big Ten Network. The show, presented by the Office of the Vice President for Communications and produced by Michigan Productions, aired on the Big Ten Network and was dedicated to highlighting the people, research, outreach, and events that make the University of Michigan a premier institution of higher learning.
The Michigan Public Media records document the unit's operations and provide varied examples of its creative output. The materials will be useful to researchers interested in news and information about the University of Michigan as well as for those exploring how a major research institution communicates its mission and activities to the general public. The record group is comprised of the Out of the Blue series and the Archived Website series.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Universities and colleges--Michigan.; Michigan Public Media.; Television broadcasting--Michigan.; University of Michigan--Buildings.Buildings.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan--Research.Research.; University of Michigan--Students.Students.
Genre Terms:
Digital moving image formats.; Television programs.; Websites.
- Out of the Blue
  The Out of the Blue series (112.4 GB) consists of three seasons of Michigan Public Media's program Out of the Blue: the Michigan Difference, which originally aired on the Big Ten Network from 2008-2009 to 2010-2011. Each episode (with the exception of season two, episode ten) consists of three separate segments that focus on exceptional people, research, programs, and/or events at the University of Michigan. The featured segments often include interviews with subjects, guided tours of facilities, and relevant background information. Season one (2008-2009) consists of ten episodes that cover medical advancements, new technologies, the arts, the environment and sustainability, and engineering projects at the University of Michigan. Of note is this season's coverage of the University of Michigan Museum of Art, which celebrated a grand reopening after its expansion (see episodes three and five). Season two (2009-2010) consists of fifteen episodes that document a variety of departments and people across campus. Of particular note are episodes related to sustainability efforts on campus (five), the Prison Creative Arts Project (ten), and the university's relationship with China (fourteen). Finally, season three (2010-2011) includes twelve episodes that with features on programs at the Ross School of Business, science, technology, economics, policy, arts, and minorities and outreach programs. In-depth examinations on U-M and the Peace Corps (episode six) and film-making in Michigan (episode one) will be of interest particular. The individual episodes can be downloaded from the University of Michigan's institutional repository ("Deep Blue") as QuickTime .mov files.
  - Season 1
    - Episode 01, 2008-2009
      - Feature 1: Dr. Karin Muraszko discusses the challenges of pediatric neurosurgery and her personal journey through disability. Her story is one of innovation and inspiration.
      - Feature 2: Dr. Philip Gingerich discusses the fascinating discoveries his team has made regarding the connections between primitive whales, sheep, and hippos.
      - Feature 3: Saturday Morning Physics is a Saturday morning series that attracts crowds each week with illuminating demonstrations that explain the science of our world.
    - Episode 02, 2008-2009
      - Feature 1: Dr. Deborah Ball, Dean of the School of Education, discusses her development of the elementary mathematics lab to improve methods of teaching math in primary education.
      - Feature 2: Professor, dancer, and choreographer, Peter Sparling discusses his imaginative new multimedia dance work, Climbing Sainte--Victoire.
      - Feature 3: The student group MPowered empowers student entrepreneurship with startling results.
    - Episode 03, 2008-2009
      - Feature 1: Preview the expansion and relaunch of the University of Michigan's Museum of Art, which seeks to redefine how museums relate to the communities that house them.
      - Feature 2: The University of Michigan's Curator of American Culinary History, Jan Longone, tells us how America's history can be traced through its food.
      - Feature 3: Professor of Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering Michael Parsons shares his elegant solution for preventing invasive species from hitching rides in ballast water: create a ballast--free ship.
    - Episode 04, 2008-2009
      - Feature 1: Professor Michael Bernitsas' VIVACE project turns what is normally the bane of a marine engineer's existence into a potential solution to our energy needs.
      - Feature 2: The University of Michigan's musical theatre department has grown from Brent Wagner's singular vision to one of the top programs in the nation. For the program's 25th anniversary, Michigan's Broadway star alumni return to their roots to perform alongside current students in a song and dance celebration.
      - Feature 3: How do you get people to explore a subject that would normally fall outside their area of interest? The University of Michigan does it with theme semesters.
    - Episode 05, 2008-2009
      - Feature 1: Looking for new ways to give back, a group of exceptional biomedical engineering students forms an organization designed to benefit doctors and their patients halfway around the world.
      - Feature 2: The University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute (UMTRI) is developing a collision avoidance system that will make our roads safer. Lead researcher Jim Sayer explains the system and takes it for a test drive.
      - Feature 3: The University of Michigan is redefining the role its Museum of Art plays in the life of the campus and the community. If the grand reopening is any indication, there are plenty of exciting things in store.
    - Episode 06, 2008-2009
      - Feature 1: A group of graduate students from the U-M's College of Architecture and Urban Planning are working to create a sustainable community--based food system in Detroit so that everyone--no matter what their income or transportation challenges--can get better nutrition.
      - Feature 2: Four years ago, Professor Thylias Moss, a renowned poet and a MacArthur and Guggenheim fellow, had a revelation that inspired her to jump off an artistic career cliff. Her new exploration of multimedia communication fused with poetry has transformed her work and her teaching.
      - Feature 3: FestiFools explodes onto Ann Arbor's Main Street with enormous paper mâché creatures and hundreds of participants from across the community.
    - Episode 07, 2008-2009
      - Feature 1: The University of Michigan has often blazed a trail for advances in medicine. Now a new generation of researchers is working on the cutting--edge technology of stem cells to better understand stem cell biology and to develop therapies and cures for some of our most intractable diseases. Someday the life they save May be yours.
      - Feature 2: Environmental Interpretive Center on U-M's Dearborn campus uses the former grounds of an auto baron's mansion to teach students and community members about environmental succession and stewardship. Professor Orin Gelderloos strolls the grounds and shows the changes that time and nature have wrought.
      - Feature 3: Talking Points uses standard cell phones to access the internet so visually impaired people can get information about where they are going and the businesses they're passing. But the system's creators are realizing that sighted people May want to use their invention too.
    - Episode 08, 2008-2009
      - Feature 1: Professor Nick Tobier is interested in pushing the boundaries of art and himself. He works with the ephemeral canvas of daily life and real people in communities by creating unusual and unexpected encounters. In the process, he changes both those who come upon his work, and himself.
      - Feature 2: Husk is a group of five University of Michigan MBA graduates who are taking their class project to market. Using discarded materials to create high value insulation, the Husk team has already won a number of local and national business plan competitions--complete with large cash prizes. If they succeed, Husk will be green in more ways than one.
      - Feature 3: In a university filled with people coming up with all kinds of inventions and discoveries, what is the cheapest and quickest way to get a great idea on its feet? If it involves a 3--dimensional object, the folks at the 3--D Prototyping Lab often have the solution.
    - Episode 09, 2008-2009
      - Feature 1: Teaching doctors and first responders to triage on-site disaster victims by doing physical simulations is expensive and time consuming, so training opportunities are rare. But by using the remarkable technology of their Virtual Reality CAVE, University of Michigan researchers have developed a new simulation program that will help save lives.
      - Feature 2: University towns tend to be great places to live and Ann Arbor is no exception. Between the wide array of students, faculty, and staff drawn to the city from all over the world and the variety of interests and activities they bring with them, there's something for everyone in Ann Arbor.
      - Feature 3: In an era where cell phones can take and send pictures and access the internet, what could future generations of communication devices do? Researchers at the U-M's School of Information have some answers.
    - Episode 10, 2008-2009
      - Feature 1: By conservative estimates, some 87,000 people in the United States are wrongfully imprisoned. Not only are the lives and families of innocent people being ruined, every taxpayer is absorbing the considerable expense of keeping these people behind bars. Meanwhile, the real criminals remain free. But what can be done? The University of Michigan Law School's Innocence Clinic--the first of its kind at any American university--is addressing the problem. Will they succeed in their first--ever case?
      - Feature 2: The Hopwood Awards are the richest collegiate writing awards in the country. Open to both graduate and undergraduate students, the Hopwoods have been jump--starting literary careers since the 1930s. The list of past winners is studded with many familiar names and runs from New York to Hollywood and all places in between.
      - Feature 3: Construction is booming on the University of Michigan campus. From renovating iconic structures like Michigan Stadium to new concepts in education and hospitalization, the University builds the campus of tomorrow while providing jobs today.
  - Season 2
    - Episode 01, 2009-2010
      - Feature 1: Since the U-M Biological Station in Northern Michigan has provided a unique setting for innovative research in environmental science. Their multi-faceted approach to studying carbon sequestration is providing a breadth of empirical data to help better guide future environmental policies., 1909
      - Feature 2: The team at the Center for Motor Behavior and Pediatric Disabilities provides children with Downs Syndrome and Autism Spectrum Disorder with the opportunity to enjoy an important rite of passage. The Center also captures important data that can help inform policy to improve the physical education and well being of children with Downs and ASD.
      - Feature 3: Marine and Aerospace researchers at U-M develop a wholly unique method for gathering oceanic data.
    - Episode 02, 2009-2010
      - Feature 1: Students and faculty at the School of Social Work are partnering with the Michigan Prisoner Reentry Initiative to fight recidivism and help convicted felons find a new, productive place in society.
      - Feature 2: The Kelsey Museum recently enjoyed a major building renovation, and in the process developed new ways to serve the university and the community at large with its impressive collection of artifacts.
      - Feature 3: We've all heard about, maybe even used, cellular phone applications. However, this app, developed by U-M students, has an altogether altruistic purpose.
    - Episode 03, 2009-2010
      - Feature 1: The University of Michigan Men's Glee Club celebrates 150 years of music, tradition, camaraderie, and excellence.
      - Feature 2: The U-M is home to the Knight Wallace Journalism Fellows Program, which gives mid-career journalists an opportunity to examine their career goals and expand their knowledge and experiences.
      - Feature 3: The University of Michigan's Papyrology collection is a unique body of ancient manuscripts that gives us a window into the past through the writings of scholars and everyday people (features the late Traianos Gagos)
    - Episode 04, 2009-2010
      - Feature 1: How do cities adapt to decreasing populations? The Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning seeks viable solutions for changing communities.
      - Feature 2: Professor Dan Klionsky finds success using active teaching methods to teach science to non-science majors.
      - Feature 3: Professor Georg Essl's iPhone Orchestra puts interdisciplinary thought into finding a new use for a common object.
    - Episode 05, 2009-2010
      - Feature 1: The U-M is committed to improving sustainability campus wide. Take a tour of some of the latest innovations and new construction that reflects this commitment to go beyond LEED.
      - Feature 2: How do you move beyond words and plans to actions? You get students, faculty, and staff actively involved in the university's sustainability efforts.
      - Feature 3: The Big House is one of the most recognizable structures on campus. But this home to the Maize and Blue has also gone green
    - Episode 06, 2009-2010
      - Feature 1: The University Musical Society is one of the oldest presenters of performing arts in the country. We learn about this organization's history and how they are re-defining their role in the community.
      - Feature 2: The U-M School of Education is revamping their curriculum to better prepare teachers to manage the challenges they face in the classroom.
      - Feature 3: Students at the U-M participate in a special program that gives them the benefits of an international educational experience from Central Campus in Ann Arbor.
    - Episode 07, 2009-2010
      - Feature 1: At the Michigan Engineering Zone, high school students learn about engineering and get geared up to compete in the FIRST Robotics Competition.
      - Feature 2: We look back at the 120 year history of the Michigan Daily, a student run newspaper, and examine how it is moving forward in the face of a swiftly changing industry.
      - Feature 3: A new type of artificial foot improves amputee's ability to walk
    - Episode 08, 2009-2010
      - Feature 1: We watch how the Business Engagement Center connects the business community with the vast pool of talent and resources at the U-M. Feature
      - Feature 2: At Tornado Camp, a professor takes students out in the field to document extreme weather and use technology in an innovative way.
      - Feature 3: A team of U-M students take their extracurricular project underwater with a human submarine
    - Episode 09, 2009-2010
      - Feature 1: Michigan Radio and the Center for Middle Eastern and North African Studies's "Muslims in Michigan" project is an attempt to improve the public's understanding of one diverse group of Michigan residents.
      - Feature 2: Through her research, Professor Bettina Cornwell of the U-M School of Kinesiology discovers that children are able to identify brands much earlier than previously believed.
      - Feature 3: with the introduction of bendable concrete, the most ubiquitous construction material known to man gets an update that makes it safer and more durable
    - Episode 10, 2009-2010
      (Only contains one featured segment.)
      - Feature: U-M professors Janie Paul and Buzz Alexander lead the Prison Creative Arts Project, which engages prisoners in the creation of art and presents their works for an annual exhibit of prison art at the U-M. The story features art from inside Michigan prisons and is a powerful window into the often invisible experience of the thousands of men and women behind bars in this state
    - Episode 11, 2009-2010
      - Feature 1: The Detroit Observatory, built in on the U-M's Central Campus, is the centerpiece of President Henry Tappan's vision. Tappan saw the observatory as a vehicle to transform the U-M into one of the top science and research universities in the US. The creation of the Detroit Observatory thus marked a definitive turning point for the U-M to become recognized as a leader in science, research, and technology., 1854
      - Feature 2: The Wolverine Venture Fund is a multi-million dollar venture capital fund operated directly out of the Ross School of business. The WVF invests primarily in early-stage, emerging growth companies. The Fund invests with the active involvement of MBA students, faculty assistance, and an advisory board composed of professional venture capitalists and entrepreneurs.
      - Feature 3: The Tango Club, a volunteer-based student organization, is dedicated to the philosophy that "tango is not a commodity but rather an art form to be shared freely." The student run club fosters leadership through a firm appreciation of the talents, abilities, and motivations of their members
    - Episode 12, 2009-2010
      - Feature 1: Dr. Victor Strecher is the U-M Distinguished University Innovator for 2010. He is a professor of health behavior and health education in the School of Public Health, professor of health behavior in the Department of Family Medicine in the Medical School, and also a successful entrepreneur, having launched HealthMedia in 1998. We learn about his work and how it is inspired by personal experience.
      - Feature 2: Catherine Badgley is an Assistant Professor of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology whose research into crop yields from organic farming versus large, agribusiness farming has turned common assumptions on their head. Her research indicates that organic farming actually yields more produce per acre than "traditional," large-scale agribusiness farming that uses pesticides, herbicides and genetically modified crops.
      - Feature 3: The University of Michigan Women's Rowing team is not only accomplished athletically, they're accomplished academically as well. Currently ranked 11th in the country in their sport, they also have a roster filled with student/athletes who have won numerous University, Big Ten and national academic honors.
    - Episode 13, 2009-2010
      - Feature 1: Girls in Science and Engineering (GISE), a program run through Women in Science and Engineering (WISE), is a week long summer program for middle school girls focused on hands-on activities that are educational, fun and challenging. The "campers" elect a "Focus Project" in a particular area of study (e.g. chemistry, computer science, engineering, human genetics, physics, and robotics.) The focus projects are planned and taught by U-M faculty, staff and students. During the week, the campers explore the U-M campus, tour dynamic labs and learn about science and engineering careers.
      - Feature 2: In an effort to help Michigan realize its economic potential, the University of Michigan has established the Office of Technology Transfer (OTT.) Tech Transfer is comprised of a group of specialists in the areas of technology licensing, intellectual property law and business formation. The Tech Transfer team provides professional services in these areas to the University of Michigan faculty and research scientists. Tech Transfer engages with the inventors in every phase of technology transfer from initial consultation to technology assessments, licensing, marketing and start-up business enterprises.
      - Feature 3: "Bio-Artography" refers to the genre of images captured from microscopic research of tissue studies. These extraordinary and dazzling images of deep "inner space" are developed, enlarged, printed and framed for art exhibitions and sale
    - Episode 14, 2009-2010
      - Feature 1: The Joint Institute project of U-M Engineering and Shanghai Jiao Tong University (SJTU) goes back 10 years, and the Joint Institute was officially launched 5 years ago when President Coleman personally signed the documents in a public ceremony in Shanghai.
      - Feature 2: School of Public Health Associate Dean Dr. Matthew Boulton travels to Tianjin, China with 7 residents, doctoral and graduate students to conduct research on measles and other infectious diseases as well as participate in capacity building with Chinese institutions.
      - Feature 3: In President Mary Sue Coleman announced an expansion of the research partnership between U-M and SJTU. We learn the details from President Coleman and Madame Ma, Secretary of Education at Jiao Tong University., July 2010
    - Episode 15, 2009-2010
      - Feature 1: Celebrating its 10th Anniversary with sold-out performances, Shakespeare in the Arb brings together non-theater students from across campus along with Ann Arbor community members to perform "A Midsummer Night Dream".
      - Feature 2: With diversity being a key goal in the University of Michigan's plan for developing students for a globalized society, the Center for Educational Outreach has put in place a multi-faceted approach to reach out to youth and engages them in preparing for a college education as an integral part of their future.
      - Feature 3: At the end of World War II, thousands of veterans returned to the United States in pursuit of a college education. The University of Michigan leaped into action, constructing temporary and permanent housing to accommodate the former soldiers-who brought a new seriousness to the college atmosphere.
  - Season 3
    - Episode 01, 2010-2011